This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Hello, this is Priyanka Raghavan for
Software Engineering Radio. Today we
have Matthew Adams on the show. He's
currently the head of security
enablement at Citi where his role
focuses on driving security innovation
across emerging technologies such as
generative AI, blockchain, and quantum
computing. He's here on the show because
of his interest in finding practical
applications for LLMs in cybersecurity.
And today we're going to be discussing
using LLMs in threat modeling, focusing
on his popular work STRIDE GPT.
Welcome to the show, Matt. I'm so
excited to have you here.
Thanks, Priyanka. Great to be here.
We have done a show episode 416 on
threat modeling with Adam Shostack. Uh
this is nearly about 4 years back. So
looking forward to your take on this
topic and therefore we'll start with
some basic questions. The first one
being, what is threat modeling?
So for me, threat modeling is really
about having a structured process to
identifying potential security risks and
vulnerabilities in systems. And that's a
long way of saying, let's look at what
can go wrong and how we can address
those issues to prevent them or at least
lessen their impact. And I think for me
it's easy to get wrapped up in the
complexity of threat modeling,
particularly at the enterprise level,
but I think it's important to remember
that we do threat modeling all the time
as humans.
So a common example I I like to use is
if you're driving your car into a rough
part of town,
you're not going to leave it unlocked
when you leave it. You're going to lock
the doors, you maybe even might decide
that the level of threat is sufficient
for you to buy you know, something that
fixes the steering wheel. Maybe you if
you live there for long enough, you
might even have an immobilizer attached
to the car. All of these things, they
just kind of fit into your natural
threat model around the world. And
there's really no reason why we can't
apply that similar approach of balancing
risks to mitigations when we're building
systems as well.
Great, that's a super analogy, but one
of the things we see is that threat
modeling is not done very often.
And therefore, just wanted to ask you,
why do you think it's important to do
threat modeling for say software
engineers as well as say software teams?
I think probably the primary reason is
that it's just much easier and cheaper
to find security issues during the
design phase where you would typically
start your threat modeling process. When
I was much earlier in my career, I was
involved as a security consultant to the
smart metering program in the UK, and
threat modeling was a really key part of
that program because at the end, we were
going to take millions of metering
devices and install them into people's
homes. And so, the cost and the impact
of getting a design decision wrong at
that point because we hadn't fully
considered the threats to that system in
the round, would have stretched into
billions of pounds and a tremendous
amount of disruption. So, you know, I
think that's a really good example of
why you want to do this as a discipline
and to do it earlier in the process, the
better.
When we had Adam Shostack on the show,
episode 416, it was recorded by another
host. I found one question very
interesting. The question was, what type
of applications would benefit from
threat modeling? And he replied, the
ones that use technology. Which is maybe
tongue-in-cheek, but what do you have to
say about that? What are your thoughts?
So, I'd agree with that, but I think
there's also a cost-benefit analysis to
be done to threat modeling as well. And
while you might want to do threat
modeling for all of those systems. I
don't think you can always justify the
benefit that it brings because of the
cost of the exercise. And we'll come on
to my tools and the efforts that I'm
making in that area to make it simpler
and cheaper to do threat modeling. But
certainly at this point in time for the
most organizations, it's
cost-prohibitive because of the level of
security expertise that you need to go
and look at every system that involves
technology.
Just to follow up on that, you said it's
a bit cost-prohibitive. So if I'm a
small startup and I am running a whole
set of tools like SonarQube for doing my
static analysis and then CodeQL or
Dependabots for my SCA, which is the
software composition analysis, and then
maybe I use one of these open-source
tools like OWASP ZAP, and then run my
APIs or UIs through that. Now, if I do
all of this, will I still benefit from
the threat modeling exercise?
Yeah, so it sounds like you're building
up a really good stack of security tools
there. But for me, you need to ask the
question of where do you know where to
deploy those tools and where they're
going to be effective and to protect
which assets. There's also the question
of will they be effective against the
types of threats that affect your
system? So it's, you know, perhaps not
good to deploy one type of tool when
it's not going to be effective against a
particular type of attack. And threat
modeling really helps to dig into those
questions and give you answers. And
that's why I really like it as a
discipline because particularly over my
career, I think the focus has moved from
just being compliant or just getting
that certification against ISO 27001 or
SOC 2 or whatever it is to actually
being able to demonstrate the value of
security to the organization. And if you
can tie the risks that your organization
faces or that your system faces to the
mitigations that you're deploying and
explain that in a logical way, I think
that goes an incredibly long way.
So then, is it something that you just
do once like a high-level activity or do
you do it multiple times?
So for a lot of organizations, again
going back to the constraints and you
know, sometimes how difficult it is to
do threat modeling, it can be a one-off
activity that's done at the inception of
a system. That definitely isn't the
optimal way to do it, but I fully
recognize that for many organizations,
time and resource constraints are going
to drive that frequency of threat
modeling rather than having
set criteria for guaranteeing when a
threat model should be triggered. And I
think in an ideal world, what you would
want to do is to get closer to the point
where
your threat model is triggered by
even quite small changes to your
application or the code base of that
application, and you might even think
about initiating a mini threat modeling
exercise for each commit to a code repo,
for example. You could even take it to
that level rather than the more
traditional whiteboard-driven approach
that perhaps many of your listeners are
familiar with.
So, the last question I want to ask you
and this the context that I'm setting up
is we have a lot of apps right now.
Everyone wants to create a chatbot. They
just know a little bit of Python and
want to create a little chatbot. So, is
there a set different kind of
threat modeling that you would have to
do for applications that are built or
use LLMs or maybe GenAI? What should we
be thinking about? Is it different or
would it follow a similar pattern?
I think the fundamentals remain the
same. There are some subtleties and
unique aspects, particularly because of
the emergent nature of those
technologies, and there are some
particular risks around prompt
injection, model theft that I think
we're still trying to come up with good
answers and good mitigations to. But in
terms of that fundamental approach that
I outlined at the start of how does your
system look overall and what defenses do
you need to put in place to protect it?
I think it's still the same.
I was reading this thing called the
threat modeling manifesto today on OWASP
just, you know, preparing for this show.
It asks you like if you're building an
application, you should ask yourself
four questions. One is what are you
building? What are the risks for what
you're building? And then how would you
mitigate those risks? And are you happy
with the analysis? But like for a lay
person, what are the basic elements of a
threat model and how can I go about
answering this?
Yeah, Sophie, let me break that down. So
in terms of the what there, I think
there are a few core elements to almost
every threat model. So what is it that
you're trying to protect first of all?
So what is it? The assets in the system?
That could be the availability of the
systems themselves. It could be the data
that's contained within them. Then
typically, you'd look at defining a
trust boundary around those assets. So
the point at which you consider
different parts of the system to be
trustworthy. And there might be a
difference between the public internet
and your own private cloud type
environments. And there may even be
separate trust boundaries inside your
environment. So a particular enclave for
storing secrets or other highly
sensitive information. I think you then
look at the attack surface across each
of those elements and bearing in mind
those trust boundaries. So how could you
be attacked? Is there an obvious ingress
point into that environment? So there
might even be several ingress points. We
might also think about internal attack
surfaces as well. And then that brings
me on to threat actors within that
system or even externally to it and the
capability that they have to attack that
system and the techniques that they
might use. I think that's another key
component, and you probably think about
then the types of attacks that they
might use. So, you know, different
frameworks that perhaps we'll come on to
that talk about those different types of
attacks. And finally, and this is a key
part of the threat modeling process, you
then also want to think about the
mitigations. So, it's not just about
enumerating all of the threats. To
really deliver the value of the process,
we need to really consider the
mitigations and and how we can deliver
those as well.
So, if I were to summarize it, you need
to find the your assets, your threat
boundaries, then you talked a little bit
about the attack surface, and that gives
you like your threats, and then the
threat actors, which is important, and
finally, mitigations. This is super to
start off on the definitions of the
basic elements of a threat model. And if
one were to go and Google threat
modeling methodologies, there are scores
of them out there. There's something
called STRIDE, there's something called
PASTA, there's DREAD, and so on and so
forth. But, this methodology called
STRIDE, which is what your tool is also
built on, seems to be very popular. So,
could you maybe explain that to us?
Yeah, I think I would go so far as to
say that STRIDE is probably the most
well-known threat modeling methodology.
The key for that really, I think, is
that it's been around for a long time.
First and foremost, it's had time to get
the adoption and the groundswell of fans
behind it. And at its heart, it's just a
really simple framework that I think is
readily understood by people of all
disciplines. You don't need to be a
security expert to understand that it's
trying to help you enumerate threats and
different types of threats to your
architecture. And I think that's really
where its strength lies.
Is that something that you can like list
out for us? Like, it's an acronym.
STRIDE stands for different things.
Maybe you could tell us what each one
is.
So, the S is for spoofing, the T is for
tampering, the R is for repudiation, the
I is for I forget now.
Information disclosure.
Thank you, information disclosure.
Denial of service and then you're really
testing my knowledge
and I've forgotten the E as well.
Elevation of privileges.
Elevation of privilege, thank you. Yes,
and so I think that really helps to then
draw out the different types of threats
to the system across quite a wide range.
There's also a more recent evolution of
it which is called STRIDE LM where in
addition to those five you also add
lateral movement as well because of the
importance of that vector in terms of
threat actors being so successful at
compromising and moving quickly through
a system. So I think that's also a
recent addition that that people might
want to take a look at.
Okay.
I'll definitely add that to the show
notes. But one other thing I wanted to
ask you was one observation I noticed
that a lot of these methodologies,
whether it's STRIDE or DREAD, they seem
to be coming out of Microsoft. Any
insights on why you think this happened?
I think that's because probably
Microsoft were really pivotal in terms
of bringing security into the software
development process. And again, this
goes back to the 1990s and Bill Gates
released a famous or infamous memo
called trustworthy computing across
Microsoft that really emphasized that
his belief that if Windows and in fact
if Microsoft were going to succeed as a
company, then people needed to have
trust in their systems. And they then
started, you know, given the resources
that they had as well, I think they had
the technical ability but also the
funding and the opportunity then to go
away and come up with some key
methodologies such as STRIDE and DREAD.
I think they were both of theirs. So
yeah.
Interesting, I didn't know that but I'm
going to Google that and maybe add that
to the show notes. And now I have to get
to what was your motivations or idea for
coming up with your open source
repository stride GPT. What How did you
come up with this idea of using LLMs for
threat modeling?
Yeah, so this was around the time of
probably GPT-3.5
and ChatGPT coming out. So, I think
we're pretty much at the 2-year
anniversary of that now. And what I was
looking for was a use case in
cybersecurity that I thought would be a
good use case to apply these new tools
and techniques to. And looking back over
my career as a security consultant and
more recently a security architect, one
of the processes that I felt could
deliver huge value as we've talked about
and one of the processes that I felt
people or lots of teams really struggled
with was threat modeling. And so, that's
really where the two ideas came
together. And yeah, stride GPT was born.
Great. Um your open source repository of
course is so widely popular with threat
modeling enthusiasts, including me. And
one thing is it's very simple to use as
one of the users. But another thing that
I've also noticed talking to other
people who also use the tool is a lot of
us have started embracing this more than
say the traditional tools like the
Microsoft threat modeling tool. I think
that's the name, right? Yeah. Do you see
the same thing when you talk with people
who use your tool?
In terms of why it's perhaps more
readily adopted, yeah. I think because
I've tried to make it incredibly simple
and again drawing on that experience of
working with development teams and
taking them through threat modeling
processes and sitting in half-day
workshops more than I would care to
remember. There was often that challenge
around what do we mean by threat
modeling as security professionals and
you start with a blank sheet of paper
and you're then trying to articulate
what you mean by particular type of
threat and you go through that process.
And when I was making stride GPT, my
focus was really on how do we make it as
easy for a developer to use or a
non-security professional to use as
possible. And I think that's why, in
comparison to things like the Microsoft
Threat Modeling Tool or OWASP Threat
Dragon, which is another modeling tool,
it's just so much easier to adopt
because the barrier to entry is as low
as I can possibly make it. And I've used
those other tools. I've been with teams
that have used them, and there's
definitely a learning curve. It's like
any software package that you need to
use, but for stride GPT, you just need
to describe your application, which a
developer, an engineer, should
understand the core elements of the
application, the core functionality, and
that's all you need to do to get it to
produce a threat model.
So, I think that gives us a good segue
to go into stride GPT. The first thing I
wanted to ask you is what are the
typical inputs that one would give to
the tool, and what is the output?
Yeah, so that input, as I said, is is
really just the application description.
That's the starting point for the whole
threat modeling process through stride
GPT. And you can generate that
description either manually, so you can
just type it in. You could copy and
paste it from a confluence page or from
some existing documentation that you've
got. Or I've also introduced some
features that make it even simpler and
quicker to produce that description,
which is you can upload a diagram, so an
architecture diagram of your system, and
then there will be a separate call to
the language model to produce a
description of that architecture to then
feed into the threat modeling process.
So, you can even do a threat model
without writing a single word of a
description. Latterly as well, I've also
added a feature where you can provide
the URL of a GitHub repo and provide a
GitHub API key, and the tool will then
go off and just read through the
contents of that repo and then generate
a description again based on the
contents of that. So, that's sort of the
key input. You can also then define some
additional metadata about the app, and
that's really just to help the threat
modeling process. So, for example, what
type of app is it? Is it a cloud-native
app? Is it serverless? Is it, you know,
a standard web application? All of those
things I think just help to set the
context for the threat modeling process.
And then, once you've done that and
you've provided that description, the
outputs are either a basic list of
STRIDE threats, so typically maybe two
or three for each category within the
STRIDE framework, but you can also then
go into different tabs, and these aren't
strictly part of the STRIDE methodology,
but they are part of a broader threat
modeling methodology for many teams, and
so there are things like attack trees
which present a hierarchical view of
different types of attacks. Those can be
easily generated. I also provide the
ability to generate a DREAD assessment.
So, that takes the threats that have
been generated during the first phase
and will risk score them and prioritize
them based on that risk score. You can
of course generate the mitigations. As I
mentioned, that's absolutely key to the
process. And lastly, you can also
generate and output some test cases,
which I think is a really interesting
part because that then starts to close
the loop on the threat modeling process
where not only have you generated your
threats, you're generating your
controls, but then you have a list of
tests that you can execute to verify
continuously, potentially, those
mitigations are in place.
Okay, interesting cuz the tests which
are generated are they based on a
language or is it more like a test
specification?
So, they're written in a syntax called
Gherkin, which
Okay, yeah.
uses, I imagine, particularly some of
your listeners that are familiar with
writing test cases will be familiar with
Gherkin. But it uses a structure of a
set of verbs to articulate to the test
or the scenario that you want to test.
And it's just a really nice way of
articulating the types of things that
you would want to test for. You then
need to turn that into a piece of code
to go and verify that test. Ideally a
piece of code, it could be something
else, but ultimately you're probably
looking for a way to automate and
execute that consistently.
This is great. So,
you give it an input and then you also
get the threats as outputs as well as
the mitigations. And like you said, you
also have some test cases available to
test.
This is where I wanted to ask you maybe
a specific example with the teams you've
worked with or you've interacted with
that use the tool which solved a
particular security problem. Like what
here I wanted to ask was a better
version of if you are building a web
application and you had a user interface
that talks to a
back end for front end that talks to an
API and then you want to protect the
user interface from the user. So, you're
putting in a firewall. If you describe
the application well, will it give you
mitigations like I can suggest you that
you have a good firewall of this
particular type and therefore that
reduces your vulnerability. Would the
mitigations be very specific?
So, we can maybe talk about like how you
can improve the overall performance of
the tool, but in general what the tool
is doing is it's leveraging the base
training data from the foundation model
that you're using when you're calling
the LLM. So, stride GPT supports a
number of leading foundation models. So,
either the GPT model series, it will
also support Gemini models, some from
Mistral as well. There's even the
capability to integrate it with some
local models if you're running a tool
like Ollama, but really what we're
leveraging is the general security
knowledge that's trained into those
models. So, if you want to go really
specific, you're going to need to
provide some additional context. But
even with the foundation, the
fundamental knowledge that's in those
models, I've seen teams use it to
generate novel valid threats that
haven't appeared in previous threat
models that they've produced for a
system and that they've, you know,
definitely seen value from as a result
of that.
Would that be by giving a better input?
No, so even just from running it as a
like the standard description, just
describing the application and running
the tool,
I think people often focus on the
inconsistencies of working with large
language models, but actually there are
lots of inconsistencies in people and
sometimes they just have a bad day and
they miss something during the threat
modeling process. And we found a couple
of examples of that with various uses of
the tool where they've then gone back
and looked at it and gone, yes, of
course, that is absolutely a valid
threat and, you know, that's one that we
should definitely pick up next time. And
that was done even with, you know, a
relatively straightforward description
of the application.
So, I just wanted to maybe I'll talk a
little bit with another example just to
kind of bring it to light. I was using
the tool and I have an example, this is
just one of my hobby projects that I've
been doing and I was trying to feed that
to the stride model and what I have is
it's this application that is built as a
web application and the data is not
something that is I would call it almost
like internal data. It's not public, but
it's something that's used that I only
like my services to know about. And the
authentication that I used for this was
SSO authentication and the tool
suggested as a mitigation because of
given SSO authentication that, you know,
I should probably slap on MFA with it,
which is good. But knowing my
application, I think it was maybe a bit
excessive. It's good enough just having
the SSO.
So, the question I'm asking you is
sometimes the tool produces output, but
you still need to use your better
judgment when using the output, right?
I think that's a really good example of
where language models don't necessarily
grasp the risk appetite or
organizational policy and standards that
would influence the controls that you
would ordinarily implement. If you can
provide that context, then you can
address that challenge, but out of the
box, it won't understand the broader
sort of organizational concerns that you
will have or necessarily the need to
balance how you would effectively use
your security resource, and perhaps
having MFA everywhere isn't something
that you necessarily want to consider.
So, here I wanted to ask you about an
example where you said when we talk
about Gen AI and
actually large language models, one of
the problems that people often complain
about is hallucinations.
So, are there any
tips that you'd suggest to reduce this
because that can obviously give
bad output. Because sometimes
even when you're giving the same inputs,
you don't really necessarily might get
the same output back.
Any tips for that?
As a general rule for working with large
language models, the more you put in,
the more you'll get out.
And you know, where you might
particularly see hallucinations is where
you use acronyms or other jargon that's
very specific to your company
that won't be in the training data. The
model can just get a bit confused by
what it is that you're asking it to to
assess and so you know, you might talk
about for example a vault service. Now,
it might interpret that as HashiCorp
Vault or it might also interpret it as
some CyberArk Vault or which which have
got you know, slightly different
characteristics or it might interpret it
as a physical Vault and it's really the
lack of specificity that's tripping that
up. Whereas if you can just provide that
extra bit of detail
around it's okay, you know, we're
retrieving secrets for
machine-to-machine communication and
authentication and you give it the
specific name of the service that's
doing that then that that goes a long
way to addressing that challenge of of
hallucination.
What I'm building is to overcome that
hallucination problem. Make sure that
your inputs are as specific as possible.
Avoid acronyms and
maybe give a specific example of the
tool you're using for example, could it
be a service like HashiCorp Vault or an
S3 bucket etc. Or even a PostgreSQL
database. So, the next question I wanted
to ask you is the application is built
using Streamlit. Why did you use this to
build the application?
My focus as I as I mentioned when
thinking about the concept for Strive
GPT was to look at how could I apply
LLMs to solve problems in cybersecurity.
And for me the interaction of the LLM
with the use case is more important than
the UI and I think Streamlit has a
couple of things that make it really
easy to work with in terms of quickly
building a UI. I generally work in
Python as well, so that's another
positive because it's a a Python
framework.
And
really it just makes it super simple to
get going and to deliver something
that's well presented and I think pretty
readily understandable by by users as
well. And it's also got a really nice
feature in the Streamlit Cloud as well
where you can host tools for free
providing that you don't exceed the the
container thresholds for for memory and
and compute which I think are are pretty
generous and they're ideal for POCs or
or demo tools just like Streamlit GPT.
Yeah, I was actually going to ask you
that. So, you typically where do you
deploy this? You do it on the Streamlit
Cloud, but if someone was to use your
tool, is there a danger of deploying it
onto Streamlit Cloud? They were to use
it for their organization.
So, I I wouldn't recommend using
Streamlit Cloud for production,
definitely not, but just by cloning the
repo, you can run it from a local
machine. You know, I think most people
use it on a local machine. I'm aware of
some companies that have used the Docker
container image that I provide as well.
So, you know, that typically is a is a
really way to to get that onto a
Docker environment or Kubernetes cluster
inside your enterprise. And then I think
that gives you obviously much more
confidence about the data that's going
to the tool and
and the things that might be going on
within the infrastructure to log the
inputs. I do want to say that,
you know, the one of the reasons why I
use Streamlit is that it doesn't retain
any data.
So, when you provide your API key
because I can't pay for everybody's
inference bills for OpenAI or Mistral,
whichever service you're using, but if
you provide your API key, it gets stored
in the session for that browser session.
But, if you refresh the page, it's then
removed from the session and there's no
logging of the the keys or anything else
or the information that you provide on
the back end. And that's another reason
that I really like the Streamlit
platform because as a security
professional, I don't want to be holding
other people's API keys or or system
descriptions. I just want to give them a
proof of concept tool that they can
experiment with and see the power of
applying these large language models to
to this particularly interesting problem
in cybersecurity.
And another thing which I liked about
Streamlit is also the fact that it's
since it's built on web sockets, I think
I find the speed of the UI is very fast.
The next thing I wanted to ask you which
is is something that teams ask is where
do you generally store the threat
models? Right now, the output of these
threat models if you're using the tool
is stored as an MD file. And is that
something that you would store closer to
your code repository or is that not a
good idea?
I'd say whatever would really works for
for your team and the way that you work.
So the reason why the version that's on
Streamlit produces markdown files is
because I think that's just an easy
format of output to work with and you
can take that and you can you know,
there are markdown PDF converters that
are readily available. Equally, if you
want to take it into some other format,
it's very easy to strip out the markdown
syntax and and work with that. But I'm
aware of use cases where people want to
take the threats and generate them in a
very specific structured format. So that
might be semi-structured in terms of CSV
or perhaps even JSON. And they would
then take that to import into something
like a Jira ticketing system because
what they ultimately want is for each
threat to be represented as a ticket
that they could then assign a
corresponding mitigation ticket to. So
that's one approach. Some teams also
just want really detailed confluence
pages and don't take the ticketing
approach, but they want really thorough
documentation. So I think really
whatever works for you and your team as
a workflow and the important thing is
just to get get threat modeling.
I guess the question I was also asking
was there's
some people who also worried that if
somebody gets a hand on a threat model,
they they can attack the system because
they know what the threats are. So,
should you be taking more steps to like
our back control the access to that
threat model? I guess that's where I was
coming from.
Right. Okay. Yeah. So, I think
definitely you know, threat modeling
information is certainly more sensitive
or some of the more sensitive
information that you'll have in an
organization. I'm always wary though of,
you know, having that security by
obscurity
impact and and that want to say that
your system should be designed to defend
itself whether or not the threat model
is known by an attacker. And so, yes,
just for like general in-house
management, you would probably want our
back controls around it to keep it to
your threat modeling teams and your
developers. But, ultimately, your system
should be robust enough to to survive
that information being exposed.
While you were answering this, I wanted
to ask you, where would you use this
output of the threat model? I think one
of the cases is the generation of test
cases. Anywhere else that you use the
threat models or you know, teams where
do they use the output? Apart from of
course writing the code based on the
mitigations.
Yeah, I think
we sort of touched on this already. So,
you know, perhaps in a in a more mature
threat modeling process, you would want
that record to go into a some sort of
ticketing system so that you can
identify
when you've applied the mitigations and
even when you've written then the test
cases to verify that
those mitigations are effective and
continue to be effective. I think that's
really the key output.
You have a lot of other open source
projects which are all built in Python.
For example, I have seen this tool
called AttackGen which is an incident
response tool. Can you maybe talk a
little bit about that?
So, AttackGen really came to me as
another way of helping security teams
address a problem that I'd seen
throughout my career.
And
you know, listeners that work in
financial services in the UK, which
which is a relatively small community
across the global community, will be
aware of a program that was driven by
the Bank of England around
threat-driven red teaming. So, they
would get very specific threat
intelligence that related to the UK
financial sector.
And they would then instruct a
consultancy to go and test organizations
against those specific threats. And
those were really valuable exercises,
but because of the time taken to
research and plan them, they could only
be performed for, you know, a very small
percentage of the total financial market
and and sector. But, the approach really
struck me as a as a good one because you
were actually testing against or
simulating a realistic threat to your
organization. And so, when suddenly
with, again, ChatGPT or GPT 3.5, you
suddenly get the ability to generate
text at an amazing volume,
I started think about, well, maybe we
could generate incident response testing
scenarios using these tools. And that's
really what AttackGen is. So, you will
give it a either a particular threat
actor group from the MITRE ATT&CK
framework, or if you have your own
threat intel that you know that there
are particular techniques and tactics
that you want to test, you can then
build your own custom scenario
effectively just by selecting those
techniques. And then, the tool will
within 30 seconds build you
comprehensive incident response testing
scenario that covers all of those
techniques that you specified. And it
will allow you to then tweak that as
well to your specific requirements.
Impressive. So, one of the things I did
notice in a lot of your projects, I see
one of the motivations for the
open-source LLM security tools seems to
be in reducing the time to do these
activities, right?
Do you have any numbers? For example, I
can say like for me
you know, previously I'm quite
passionate about threat modeling. I've
been doing it for quite some time.
Again, like you said, using a lot of the
tools. But the problem was it it would
always take me even for a simple project
it would take me about a By the time
that I could generate the threats, but
then you'd have a meeting with the team
and then discuss the
mitigations and the whole thing would
take even for a simple one would take me
like about a week. And now I feel that
the productivity has really increased.
I'm generating the threat model in about
5 minutes or maximum maybe 5-10 minutes.
And then once I have all the inputs, and
then it's just that question of having
that one meeting to sort of go over the
mitigations. So, for me then in terms of
productivity and where also you're not
dependent on a security professional can
say I'll tell the teams please go ahead
and generate this and more threat
modeling is done. But what would you say
in your experience,
what are the kind of numbers you're
seeing in red reduction of effort?
I'd say that's pretty representative to
what I've seen in the for a reasonable
quality threat model of most
enterprise systems and applications.
It's obviously hugely dependent upon the
input scope, but let's say that might
take you 20 to 25 hours to produce some
and work on one to produce
an adequate threat model.
Using something like Strike GPT,
conservatively, probably you could cut
that time by 75%
upwards of that even. And that's still
allowing for diligently verifying the
outputs, the risk ratings, the threats
that it generates, and so still giving
yourself a good maybe half a day to go
and do that. But, that's a huge win for
what are
expensive resources and scarce resources
within an organization if if we think of
security architects.
Um it's the similar thing if for the
incident response tool also you're
seeing similar kind of numbers?
That's probably even higher because
threat modeling is as people that have
practiced it is a relatively complex
task and there's a good amount of
some is intuition, some is experience,
and some is just down to the particular
style of the architect. It's quite an
opinionated practice. To just generate a
scenario based on a
a list of techniques from the MITRE
ATTACK framework.
The input to that is maybe
half a dozen to a dozen different
techniques from various stages of the
kill chain.
And then once you've done that, which
again you're probably getting from your
threat intel provider if you if you if
you're paying for a service like that.
Once you've done that into the tool, it
will generate that within a minute even
if you're using the most advanced model
that I support at the moment which is
the A1 preview model from OpenAI. It's
quite interesting to see the level of
difference in the in the outputs that's
generated by that model and the
additional thought that goes into or the
additional reflection that goes into
generating the model because it will
also then talk about much broader
considerations
around the scenario. So, not just how
you're going to be attacked, but if
you're running it as an exercise, which
stakeholders should you ensure in the
room, how should you plan your time, you
know, those sorts of things which when
you're using a a smaller, simpler model,
it just focuses on generating a a
realistic scenario based on the tactics.
So, yeah, I I'd say that's probably more
like 90-95%
improvement in in productivity for that
one.
This is actually a fantastic cuz I
really feel you're doing a lot for the
community and that's why I wanted to ask
you this next question. I've been
reading this blog by a person called
Ross Halelu. I follow him on Twitter and
LinkedIn and I came across one of his
blog posts which I'm going to put in the
show notes, but it's called lifting the
world out of cybersecurity poverty and
he has a quote from his blog and I'm
just going to read that because I don't
want to paraphrase it. What it says is
there is about 185,000
small businesses in the United States
which
constitutes about 99.9% of the American
businesses and small businesses pay
39.4%
of private sector payroll and generate
32.6% of known export volume. Despite
all the importance of the small business
market, I would estimate that over 90%
of the cybersecurity startups are built
as enterprise first solutions. So, was
your quest for doing a lot of these
open source LM security tools a way to
alleviate cybersecurity poverty and help
these SMBs or small business units?
I think that concept of cybersecurity
poverty is is an interesting one and and
certainly probably more with the attack
gentle
than I was aware having been a
consultant and been involved in incident
response testing scenarios and the
planning for that, how costly they are,
and also being on the client side and
having to do them as well, and knowing
that you may only get maybe one two
opportunities a year to do that kind of
exercise given the stakeholders that you
want in the room and the amount of
preparation that it takes, and then
suddenly you have this ability or it's
it struck me that you would have the
ability
to even go to the point of picking parts
of a kill chain
and that you were concerned about and
then testing those maybe just with your
security analysts and running through a
very quick scenario.
And that then became possible using that
kind of tool. So, I think there's a huge
role for for open source to play in in
helping to close that poverty gap. If
tools like stride GPT and attack gen and
and others that I've released help to do
that then, you know, I'm I'm really
happy about that. I think though that
what I'm trying to do primarily with
those tools
is address those people out there at the
moment that
I think they're they're getting fewer in
number as as the months go by, but who
look at large language models and
generative AI more broadly and say
there's no value here. I don't see the
use case.
And what I'm trying to do with these
tools is that there absolutely is value
and that these are the worst versions of
these models that we're ever going to
have to work with. And I think looking
back over
you know, nearly 20 years
there are so many things in security
that I know that security professionals
want to fix and do better, but we just
don't have the time or the resources to
do it. And I think what has emerged over
the last couple of years strikes me as
an amazing opportunity to go and resolve
a large number of those issues that have
been dogging us over the last 20 30 plus
years.
Absolutely. Couldn't have said it
better. It's fantastic. I was going to
ask you two questions to kind of wrap it
up. The first one was what are the other
open source security projects you follow
that we should look up as software
engineers or developers or architects or
teams. Are there anything that you'd
list out that I can obviously add to the
show notes?
More generally, the OWASP projects are
amazing projects. There's a huge amount
of value and I know a number of the
project leads that pour in an an amazing
amount of time and dedication to helping
those projects succeed. So, I'm sure
your listeners are aware of many of
those, but definitely worth a look at
the OWASP AI security project that's out
there, the top 10 for large language
models, and the new the newer governance
frameworks that have come out for large
language models as well. I think more
specifically, one of the projects that I
really like is a tool called Garak,
which I'm sure we'll leave a link to in
the show notes, and that is a an
open-source LLM vulnerability scanner.
And because of those
threats like prompt injection being so
new and so novel, I think it's really
really encouraging to see an open-source
project out there addressing some of
those absolutely leading-edge challenges
that that we have as security
professionals to secure those systems.
I'll make sure to add that to the show
notes. I think I found the OWASP AI
security page fantastic. I've also just
been reading it the whole day. It's
yeah, it's really useful for anyone
who's interested in how to secure
systems built using GenAI or large
language models or ML. The last question
I wanted to ask you, there's this
concept of using AI to fight AI.
It's like good AI versus bad AI. Sounds
a bit dramatic. What are your thoughts
on that?
I think we probably will get to that
point if we're not already at that point
already. It's just you know, you you
would look at
the more traditional predictive AI
that's been baked into cybersecurity
tools for actually a number of years
now. What I I we have seen on the
adversarial side is that just like
mediocre developers such as myself have
been improved greatly by having access
to large language models, then so it
seems that the lesser skilled threat
actors have been able to up their game
using large language models in terms of
improving the level of robustness of
their code, the degree of automation
that they're able to achieve, stringing
different attack types together. What I
don't think we've seen yet, though, is
nation states that are then using some
of their existing exploit data, which I
think we can safely assume that that
they have, to then train a model that's
specifically designed to leverage very
sophisticated
malware or cybersecurity attacks
against, you know, organizations or
other nations at scale. And I'm thinking
there about the something like the
Eternal Blue malware that was leaked
from the NSA. You know, if you take
exploits like that and you train models
on them, that I think will be, you know,
a significant day if and when that
occurs. And
our best bet at defenders is to look at
how we can leverage AI for the more
positive use cases of covering as many
systems as possible, making sure that
we've done everything we can to to go
through the threat modeling process,
understand where we might have issues,
and use the AI to scale our security
processes to make our defenses as as
robust as they can be.
That was really great. Thank you again
for coming on the show. I
think I'm done with my questions. Where
should people
find you on cyberspace if they wanted to
get in touch with you?
Uh so, if you find me on LinkedIn, my
profile is Matthew R.W. Adams.
Or you can find me on GitHub. I'm M.R.W.
Adams on GitHub, and you'll find the
links to my repos there. And again, I'm
I'm sure we'll drop those into the show
notes as well.
Yes. Yes, I'll definitely do that.
Thanks for listening. This is Priyanka
Raghavan for Software Engineering Radio.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.